I pledge allegiance to the flag of The United States Of America
>> and to the republic which it stands one
nation under God,
indivisible,
with liberty,
Okay,
>> thank you.
Hey Linda.
Okay,
welcome everybody to the April 28 meeting of the town of Andover Board of Finance. We do have a lot to cover today so this could go long but we'll see what we can get done in the time we have.
I'll make the time available I guess.
Our first agenda item is
public speak. I just want to again remind everybody as we often do during these meetings to try to keep it concise to the point.
And
if
needed,
we'd like to limit you to about three minutes.
If needed, we can always come back to you if you have more you'd like to say, and also as usual, try not to,
you know, reiterate too much somebody else has said just say you know I agree with, you know, that person and
try to keep it efficient.
Will have another public speak opportunity at the end of the meeting.
Okay, Amanda, do you want to go around and see if anybody has any comments?
>> Yes, okay. First up we have Kathy Palazzi and Mike Palazzi.
I'm all set.
Mike's all set.
Right, thank you.
Valerie Bruno?
Amanda,
thanks. Okay. Thank you.
Carol Lee?
All set. Thank you.
Georgette Conrad.
For once, have nothing to say.
>> Thanks for being here.
All right. Next up, Jeff McGuire.
I'm all set. Thank you, Amanda.
Thanks, Jeff.
And last but not least, Dan Foran.
I'm good. Thank you.
All right. No public speak.
>> Okay.
Thank you. Appreciate it. We will move on to agenda item number three. This is the opportunity where we have
the opportunity here to add and delete items from the agenda.
Do any of the board members have any suggestions for additions or deletions of the agenda?
Eric, are you aware of any other business we should be dealing with that's not on the agenda?
Okay, Eric's not shaking his head no.
Okay, hearing none, let's move along to item number four. This is to discuss and act upon the budget.
So there's some things we need to talk about here. Some things have changed since we had our public hearing last week.
So the agenda item A1 is to discuss feedback from the public hearing. I think all the members, board members were in attendance and heard
basically what the comments were from that meeting. Was there any other feedback that we received anyone has that they want to discuss?
Okay.
Item number four,
A2,
state legislature,
municipal funding decrease. Eric, do you want to give us a summary of that please?
Sure Amanda, can I share my screen?
All right, go ahead. Okay.
>> Okay,
so you should be looking at a table which says estimated
town ECS grants for fiscal year 2022
and 2023.
So
as
most of you know, the state has not adopted a budget yet.
The governor proposed
essentially level funding in the same ECS
formula
as last year.
However, the legislative appropriations
committee
has proposed
increasing
the overall appropriation,
but revising the ECS formula. So the long and the short of it is if you look at the first
pink column under FY 2022,
they're
predicting
a ECS grant to the town of Andover $1,936,854
which is a decrease of $67,928
in revenue to the town of Andover.
Now this is not final because the budget is not passed
and one of the questions is since they did it at such a late date and most towns have already
pretty far along in their budgeting process,
would they consider a hold harmless
for the towns that are getting reduced?
And I had a long, it was a subject of discussion,
you know, at
the Crogg Policy Board meeting today,
and we spoke to our, you know, the CROG's lobbyist,
and the lobbyist indicated she did not think,
nor did,
you know, Representative Nunez,
who is on the appropriations
committee,
did not think they were going to,
they're not really even discussing seriously
or hold harmless.
So both of them were pretty sure that this is likely to hold throughout the budget process.
But again, there's no adopted state budget.
So the
best number we have is that compared to the budget we presented
a week ago today,
our revenue will be decreased by $67,928
>> Okay, thank you, Eric.
So the
just to clarify,
hopefully everyone understood that, but the there was some discussion of what Eric called a hold harmless.
Clause, which is the idea that you know hey what we will do is, you know these towns that are losing money we're actually going to hold off on that and we'll keep the increases to the towns are getting an increases, but not redo the reductions.
You're saying now Eric that sounds like there's not much appetite for that, from what you can tell so far.
Yes. Conversations
>> in Sierra Grove, okay. Right, so far everybody we've been able to talk to that's part of the legislative process
has said that's not gonna happen.
And as you can see, lot of our neighboring towns are taking a pretty significant
hit also, but it's
up and down.
>> Yeah,
okay.
All right.
Board members, any questions for Andover here and
for Andover for Eric here. I just wanted to point out that this does affect our revenue line. It's not our expense line, but there is the
educational cost sharing line item there. We'll take a look at the budget
spreadsheet and how it impacts it
in a minute here.
No questions for Eric on that one?
Okay,
it kind of sounds like it is what it is. Just have to decide what we're going to do with it.
>> Okay, I have a question. Go ahead, Louise. Did
they specify
what the reduction was
or is it a flat dollar amount.
>> There's
a formula right and it's if you look at the Eric I didn't share this stuff I probably should have with the Board of Finance I didn't realize initially they weren't on there. But there's a there's a very specific formula based on your demographics and
issues and all those things that actually calculate
based on the demographic in the town situation
that results in that number. It's not something that somebody selects, know, it's not like somebody randomly says Andover doesn't get this anymore,
correct? Correct.
>> Okay, thanks. Yeah, I don't have a copy of the formula,
you know I read through the formula basically they're doing a couple things they're adding more funding
to
they're increasing
the kind of weighting factor for English language learners
you know, and they're adding more money to the Open Choice and some of the magnet programs,
know, and VOAG,
none of which is really applicable to us per se.
>> Any other questions or discussion?
Okay, let's move on to item
4A3,
which is the adjustment of the building admin line item.
Eric, do you want to give us a summary of that please?
>> Sure.
We had kind of worked out the numbers before the last meeting, but since we went to public hearing,
the last public hearing with the numbers we had agreed at the meeting to previous to that,
we've just refined.
We I had originally told the board it was roughly a $45,000
savings by combining those two positions.
The actual savings when you when you really account for all the items is a little more than that. So the line item for that position,
for the building admin position,
been, you know, was just a flat $45,000
decrease.
Now it reflects the actual
expected
expenditure.
So that has decreased the town's budget by three or four thousand dollars It's not much.
>> I think it's closer to 6,000
went from 45 to 39 something that line item.
>> Yeah, let me just pull it up. So I'm not speaking off the cuff.
>> Yeah, you have 39,301
we originally budgeted 45,000.
So about $5,700
Yeah,
that's about right. Okay.
>> So that's, that's the positive that's, that's a decrease in expected expenditures.
So
partially offsets the bad news, we got an educational cost sharing.
And that takes into consideration
benefits and everything, right?
>> Well, because it's a combined position and her benefits are already encompassed
in the town clerk's position.
The only thing it adds
to the benefits, accounts
for the contributions to social security and accounts for the additional contribution to MRF, the retirement
package.
So it doesn't account for additional health care benefits because it's just one person.
>> Other questions or
comments discussion on that item?
Okay, let's move on to agenda item for a four, which is to finalize the budget for the town budget meeting.
So we've got some new information today that changes our picture a little bit from the last.
The last
meeting we had which is the public hearing.
We have a net increase to our expected costs of about $61,000
So we have to decide how to treat that. So Amanda, can you let me share my screen please?
Go ahead.
>> Make sure the right one here Okay.
Alright, so this is just the department totals.
There's some notes over here on the right.
This is probably a little tough to see if you don't have a large monitor so I'm going zoom in a little bit. So two line items changed.
The first one is in the expense
option or the expense line item here
for the building department.
Excuse me, I was making sure I went through going with the right one.
There it is.
So the building department line item, you can see this in the department summary total this originally was.
I can't remember where we took this down
somewhere.
I think we allocated a little more money, this
expenditure item is at $39,301
whereas previously
it was at
about $44,043
So yeah, I'm sorry, it's probably it's a little more like $5,000 not $6,000
So
there's about a $5,000
decrease in our expenditures on this particular line item, everything else in this is remains the same,
based on what we presented at the public hearing last week.
And then the big change is actually here in the revenue column.
So in the revenue column,
have
educational cost sharing
is this line right here.
Okay,
We'd originally expected
roughly about $2,000,000
Pop over to see the actual amount.
Yeah, the educational
cost sharing was about expected to be about 2,000,000.
Well, it's the same as previous fiscal year. It's right there $2,004,007.82.
And we've got that reduction
to 1,000,009
and 36,854.
So those are the two line items that have changed in
this budget here.
The rest of those notes.
So what's the impact right now?
So we were looking at last
budget,
we're looking at a percent mill increase of 3.43
estimated mill rate of 36.83.
With this new information it takes us to 36.97
would be the required mill rate under the current budget.
So taxes would increase by that amount.
The percent mill increase rate increase would be 3.83.
I think we as a board need to decide how to handle this change
and finalize the recommended budget to be presented at the town budget meeting next Thursday.
It seems to me that we have roughly, I guess three options three main options. One is
we
reduce the
budget
for the town
or
AES or somewhere both
to accommodate that $67,000
decrease in revenue.
We can
let this tax increase stay where it is,
you know the the calculated tax increase it takes it up to 36.97
mills.
Or
we could assume,
which is kind of what I was hoping I hear something different from Eric but we could assume that
state lead is going to come through and actually do
something around that hold harmless clause and not make any changes to the recommended budget.
Obviously the risk with that last option is that the state doesn't take any action around that which is what Eric is hearing, and then we would have to
handle that
differential through some type of contingency
funding.
To me, that's not a wise option. I think we have to be a little more conservative and how we approach this. So I would think that we either need to reduce
our expenditures
or we accept this
mill rate increase
as it is
calculated here and pass that on to the town,
or we do a mix of both.
And just a reminder of the process, know, once we pass on the recommended budget to the town, we do not have the opportunity to increase it.
The town budget meeting, we can only change line items and do an overall decrease to the budget.
So that being said, that's kind of my piece.
Any comments or questions from the board?
>> I think this is Diane.
I think we need to find a place to reduce this
and live within our means.
And the only place I can think of getting it from is from the school AES budget.
I'd like to hear what everybody else thinks.
Other comments or input?
>> No, like Diane said, this is Dave. There's only two line items that have any significant cuts
and it's AES and it's a Terper and we've talked about that before.
Yes, we did.
>> We're looking for a net of about 61.
66 roughly, yeah. Oh, 66. Yeah, I thought it changes netted out.
>> No, I'm sorry. I'm sorry. It's 67 was the reduction against about a $5,000 saving 62.
Right.
>> So
the one thing is
if
we're really talking about this budget,
I mean this budget overall
in terms of the actual
total expenditures,
our year over year increase in expenditures
is about $120,000
on a $12,000,000
budget.
So we are 12 plus million dollar budget.
So for the year, year over year in terms of
expenditures,
we're up less than a percent.
You know, I get that,
you know trying to explain to the taxpayers
you know because the taxpayers are going to feel a much bigger increase
but it's not really an increase
in expenditure
overall.
>> Yep understood. It's
decrease
in revenue plus the
pulling less out of contingent not contingency sorry out of balance.
Sheri,
>> what's up? Sheri, go ahead. I have a question.
Eric, where
are we showing the $319,000
grant
that the town got
for
the American Rescue?
>> We're not because first of all, only half of that would come in this upcoming fiscal year.
Okay. And we can't use that to offset taxation.
I understand that, but I
just wanted to know,
>> you know, how that's a good point. Know, we should certainly
put that on the budget message.
Explain that a little more, Eric.
>> So
we are,
you know, according to the American Rescue Act
or American Recovery Act or whatever you call the thing,
Andover is slated
at some point to get two allotments
of
money.
Each one will be
around 159
or $160,000
but it's
money that can be spent for very targeted things
and what you absolutely can't do is use it to offset taxation.
So I guess what I'm saying is in the federal government still has not released
the actual rules
for expenditure
of that money
at least as it pertains to things that are of interest to the town.
Like there we know there's some things we can spend like we could give money to our town businesses
legally, we know we can do that,
but what we don't know is what town
stuff
we can spend that money on. We're going to be able to spend a fair bit of it to do some good for the town but we frankly don't know what the rules,
the real rules for its usage are going to be.
>> So
what's your level of confidence that we could use that money
against any of the line items in our budget versus something that we haven't considered spending money on?
>> I mean, the only things we There are some things we could potentially spend it on. Depending on how liberally or how narrowly they define categories,
we're allowed to spend it on broadband
infrastructure,
water infrastructure,
and sewer
infrastructure.
If they brought in the category,
you know,
sewer infrastructure
to cover septic systems and things like that,
we could potentially use that money for relocation
of the main septic tank that covers the town hall in anticipation
of putting a community center in. We could use that to pay for the AES
septic repairs that need to be done.
If it's,
if we have a really broad definition
of,
know, water infrastructure,
maybe we could use it to pay for the sprinkler system for the Veterans Monument.
Broadband, it's possible we can use that to
put a VoIP system in for the town.
It's also possible we can use that to fund I know the Board of Ed had to pull back a request
for
you know an updated wi fi system in the school. So all these things are possible we just honestly don't know at this point. It's kind of maddening that they haven't put out the rules yet.
>> Know.
Right stuff is in our current budget so to speak would all be future projects.
Correct.
>> Correct. Does
it get us out of this little quandary we're in right now?
>> Not that I can see.
I mean are there some things?
Yeah, I mean, guess you could
maybe reduce money in the building fund
and think that some of that expense you could shift.
But
I don't know.
I mean, if I knew, I would
strongly consider that. But
don't really know.
>> Eric, what about the trooper?
Can we reallocate
any of
that expense to that
grant perhaps?
>> I don't think we can. We can't allocate
See, here's the funny thing. We can pay
premium money
for some reason.
We can't pay employees salaries
but we can give them bonuses
basically.
If you look at what was actually in that bill you're allowed to pay essentially
for lack of a better term, a COVID bonus.
>> Like a contractual
amount maybe
in the way of security
or safety,
that kind of thing during COVID?
>> Yeah, like for
instance, they give the example of if you wanted to give your firefighters
or your EMT
personnel
premium or shift differential
during that period for having to have dealt with COVID patients because of the increased risks,
you could clearly do that.
But
I just,
you know, I feel like we're really hamstrung because we don't know what the eventual rules
are going to be. Yeah, we're going to be able to spend it on something.
I just don't know what yet.
>> I just been researching
what a couple other towns are doing,
and they're
allocating
some of that money to
the troopers
dealing with COVID
related
instances and also with
the town fire department kind of thing. The EMTs
then
whatnot that are getting called out on COVID
calls and that kind of thing. So I just bring that up because I know a couple of towns are going down that avenue and
somebody must have gotten some okay from somebody at that level
to
in order to do that, you know.
>> When you say trooper it's probably the town police department that are rather than a state trooper like we right, right, it's a town, ours is a flat fee there are no additional funds that we would have to pay due to covert related expenses at least with a trooper is that correct, Eric. That is correct.
So we can't find it hard to argue that there's COVID specific related costs there.
What
nothing nothing is worth
worth the the shot. Know, as
an idea, you gotta think about these things.
Yeah, I'm thinking out of the box.
>> Exactly. Eric,
nothing that has anything to do with
the educational
costs related to COVID in this particular grant?
>> No, I mean,
our elementary school
didn't
get any grant funding through that as far as I know. I mean Val can give you a
more, but we kind of got screwed on that.
>> And this is specifically for town costs not educational costs?
Well,
specific infrastructure costs you talked about or support costs.
>> Yeah, I mean I think potentially
maybe
backfill one or two of the things the school wanted to do but couldn't.
But
again, I don't know.
I mean, I can think of a couple of things that we potentially can spend the money on, but I'm not confident in telling you what that is until
somebody comes out with an actual set of rules. Right now the rules are like three lines:
water infrastructure,
sewer infrastructure,
broadband infrastructure.
What does that mean?
Know it's something that both cost council small pounds
and CCM
are
you know trying to weigh in on with their legislative
you know with their lobbyists trying to get as liberal a definition as possible to make it as flexible as possible but whether they succeed or not,
I don't know.
I wish I did.
>> That's a good question, Cherry. Okay.
So it
doesn't sound like you're confident that we we'd be able to apply any of that against our current budget line items.
>> No, in fact,
is the one thing that's made absolutely
clear in the act is that you can't use it to offset existing taxation.
>> So we're smart we'd be budgeting for these extra covert costs anyway so to me it's kind of a moot point, you know, I mean, yeah, record saying that if we're smart we're doing that and, you know, we'd be lucky to get the additional funds and we use appropriately but anyway that's that's
maybe.
Anyway, it is what it is.
So,
Valerie,
do you have any
insight into maybe school line items that,
you know, might be applicable fall under this.
>> I actually can sit with Eric and go over.
I'm actually the opposite of Eric I'm 100% confident that that that there's going to be places in our current budgets
to be able to spend it. I've done this twice already with ESSER grants because we got corona at the beginning and then ESSER one and two.
And, you know, it
I actually was able to put through under air quality control. It's all in how you word it, boys and girls. I was able to put in air under air quality control to get air conditioning in the preschools. I know Sherry's like, yeah. So people said you'll never get it through. I did because of the age of the children,
the heat, and the fact that they were most likely not to wear masks.
And it went through. And so,
you know, that
Sherry knows she's good at it. I'm good at it. I've done this a couple of times now. I'm 100% confident
that
we could get that $3.19,
whether it's in the town budget,
the, you know, town, whatever, school.
I
know that between the three of us, we could take stuff, Mark, that exists already in this budget and get it covered. I'm 100% confident of that because we've done it already actually three times. Esser one,
Esser two, and corona relief and got in everything that we asked for. I did not get a single one of those grants sent back for revisions.
>> We
you just have to be creative
And you also have to keep in mind,
they want you to spend this money. They don't want it back.
They seriously
on the state level are giving this money to us so that we do come up with these ideas creatively
and spend that money.
>> And, you know, you just have to be a little creative, I would think. So There's a the two of us. Sherry, they all had in there also, Mark, the the goal is, obviously, it's given to the town.
So not that you can't use it for the school, and I'm not asking you to. But the goal is to spend it on things that benefit the town. So I know that there's a a rider that's gonna be in there that's with a lot of them where you can use it. Anything that's going to increase or get you back to your
levels of tourism,
which includes signage,
which includes Right. Increase to the bridge
because that's right there by,
you know, the walk that everyone uses, to the museum, to the library,
public places, things that benefit the community. So Eric's right that they haven't given us, you know, that final document yet as to, you know, what's there, absolutely. But I know Sherry and I have done this a number of times with other grants, and I've never had to send money back, And I've always gotten them approved and has Sherry has as well. So I am confident that that we'd be able to use it. Oh, oftentimes too, social services
and anything that deals with community
health and wellness,
which would cover costs.
Mhmm.
So, you know, there is always something, Mark, that you can get through there. So once that, once that guidance comes out,
you know, if, if it comes out and, and Eric's stumped it all, there's Sherry. And then if they were looking for another mind, I'd be willing to help figure it out. But, you know, I'm sure What's mechanism
for this grant funding?
>> What do you mean mechanism?
I don't know for the town. Ours goes through e grants. So I'm not sure. My point is you have to apply for it and then you're awarded it or do you They have to give you they give you an award amount and they say this is what you're entitled to. Now fill out the grant application and give us your narrative.
And in the narrative, you give a budget summary,
budget by object. You tell them what it is you need it for.
If it's one big project, you write a smart goal.
And every grant is a little bit different.
And they do give you an opportunity,
Mark, if you do submit something
to say,
yep, nope, that's not going to fly, and then they tell you why, and it gets sent back to you. So, but it's application process you've got a limit cap, Eric that's kind of your understanding.
>> You've got an award cap and then you have to basically
>> put in an application to this right now I think so actually I think
from my reading they're going to give us the money with the value by
our expenditures
so they're gonna put that money in our account
but
then you know we have to document
>> document the end of the day. Okay. Yeah. All right. That's kind of what I was getting at either either way there's documentation either before they actually cut the check or after they cut the check.
>> You know what if that money's in your account, I would think it's a little bit, you know,
it's a little less risky than if
somebody's got to actually approve a
wire transfer somewhere right?
>> Yeah I mean I don't think there's any reason I it's not that we're not going to get it
it's just the the details of what exactly we can spend it on.
I mean it's not like we don't have an enormous amount of needs
you know that are outside what we can effectively budget for. You know the town has plenty of things it needs to spend money on.
I mean I would happily spend that entire $160,000
if they'd let me working
on town culverts
you know because
I got at least a million dollar
>> unmet need for funding for that and I don't have the money to address it. Well you know if our culverts on operation it's going to be hard to bring in those tourists I'm just saying.
>> I agree,
I agree,
You know, and if we have to put signs in the culverts even better.
So, I mean,
is really frustrating
not being farther down, not having more clarity in what's budgetable.
That's
just me.
>> Is there a breakdown of the ECS grant cut that we're looking at between
the regional and the elementary?
>> No see ECS is funded is given to a town so
there's no breakdown it's by town.
So we get a total of $2,000,000
and whether how we choose to spend that is our own business.
So it's divorced
from the revenue
side and the expense side are pretty divorced in that case.
>> We received this grant we're talking about in previous years or is this really the first year that this is on there? Just wondering if there's a line item in the revenue for it.
>> No,
there's not. This is something that's
completely
in the end
last year we got I think a total of $31,000
on the town level in coronavirus
relief funding
of which we haven't spent much of that.
But
you you
and the board of selectmen have already decided to spend that on
you know the
monument
upgrade projects.
>> So just wondering about from a from a mechanic standpoint of the budget.
I was trying to see whether land.
>> And in the other thing you have to decide is you, you, we typically don't
in the town budget
list
the completely separate funds.
Like we normally don't in the town budget account for Town Aid Road, even though that's money that comes in and money that's spent in the town side.
But we don't necessarily account for all, at least in the town's
presentation,
we don't normally
deal
with the grants and the other revenue by the elementary school.
So just we've never really done that. Maybe we should going forward
and we could if we so chose,
but we haven't typically.
>> My inclination is that you show all of your inflows and outflows. You're saying Tom and A growth really doesn't appear on there and you know it's
something we pull in and it's something we spend right?
>> That is true. That is true. And I've always wondered that.
That's always been accounted for. That's always been essentially
>> Consider why not
been accounted for in that manner doesn't mean you don't account for it.
Okay.
Out to something for future thought I'm not sure that we want to muddy muddy the waters and that with this year's budget.
So,
others proposed to the board that it sounds like there is an option, depending on our appetite for
risk that this
wouldn't be approved,
that we could in
add a line item to the revenue side for this grant.
In
some amount up to and including what is it 139,159
I think was it $3.19
>> cut in half. Yeah, it's $3.19 divided by two. Yeah, so
$159.05.
Right.
>> But if you show it
on our current budget,
what
expense
would be a legitimate expense that we would be offsetting? Or is it going to be future stuff that's not even Well, in
>> that that's the that's the question mark. And obviously,
you know,
trying to think about how we we're all talking about being creative maybe there's some creative budgeting that we need to do.
Some I hate to do the budget this way but some sort of unspecified
category we throw it into
>> you know, it doesn't it doesn't benefit
us to add another expense category I think we would know revenue side. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Well, think we just put it in as a grant, whatever the name of the grants visual name of the grant is, We had a revenue line item, it's kind of done that. What is the name of the grant here, Eric?
>> I think it's American Recoveries Act grant. American Rescue Relief Funding.
That's probably closer to the exact name.
I'm gonna call it ARF, a r r. They
>> actually use ARP,
but I always think of like the the elder agency of ARP,
but that's what they actually use on a federal level is ARP.
We might as well mimic that.
Alright, so I'm just gonna
throw this up there.
>> Now if we put it in in the revenue,
but it's not,
you know, specifically earmarked for a particular usage on the spending side.
Do we once the
once we get more clarity on where we can use it and the grants start getting written the proposals get written or whatever it is.
We need to kind of go back as a board
and approve allocating it out?
>> I mean, are you just assuming
you're going to use that money to offset taxation?
Is that what you're
>> To
me that's a that's just a non sequitur argument I don't really, I mean I understand.
I understand probably why the language is inserted and I'm certainly not a lawyer
legislator
but, you know, they're probably doing that just to prevent towns from just, they're probably
probably some kind of effort just to prevent house from like increasing their
spending,
just because they got this money.
So,
you know, but I mean, the reality is, you have these extra expenses,
you know, you're generally going to account for them in the budget. You know, maybe that's something like a tourism enhancement project or something like that, maybe that would be extra and maybe that's what their intent
is.
But it seems odd to me that you're going to have a lot of municipalities
just
coming up with these different projects to promote infrastructure.
Maybe it just really is a stimulus package in that sense.
Don't know.
>> I mean when you put it in the budget here on the revenue line and then all the numbers come out, we are using it to offset taxes so we'll set the mill rate at a low rate.
>> Is how money works though. Is how money works yeah
>> the end the end number is zero.
Right, so you you take in your stuff and you you know well unless it goes into a fund right you're you're spending,
but you know ultimately you're still going to have an offset in taxes,
it just depends on what you do with your expense side.
You know,
if you rate if what we're not doing here is we're not increasing our expenditures,
strictly because we have this extra money. And maybe that's kind of what the
legislators intent was there. But it's not clear to me.
I think that that's
kind of a semantics thing almost maybe I'm all
wet on that one.
But you know to me ultimately
you are offsetting taxes
or you know that you would have to add in to if you were to increase your expenditures the amount that this grant.
>> I mean, honestly,
I look at it a way to
accomplish
some things
that
>> we can't afford to budget for. That you wouldn't normally do in this budget year. Yeah. Right.
Yep.
But that's just me. You are the board.
>> Well, you know,
I think that being given any more guidance,
unless the guidance is pretty clear and we're just taking liberal approach to it
interpretation of it.
>> In essence, by adding this in here,
whatever we spend above and beyond this budget for a special project next year will be offset by this money because it's not going to be raised
by taxes
because the mill rate is going to be reduced.
>> So if you just put this into the budget with the intention of reducing the mill rate,
then
you know you're
making two assumptions. You're making the assumption that you can apply,
you can find some project
that's actually funded
that you could pay for with this instead of what we were budgeting for.
And
you're saying we're not going to do anything outside what's in our current budget,
Which you know may be the way you want to go.
I mean I'm not telling you that's a bad thing I'm just telling you that that is the repercussion.
>> I mean imagine a world in which we had clear guidance and we knew that we could use 159
ks to throw at culverts.
What might we do Eric is we might cut
our culvert budget
and then reinsert
the money we were getting but we can't do that right now because we don't know exactly where it's gonna go.
>> We have we just offset that 67 ks we lost through educational cost sharing which you know you could argue that are clearly
argue that our educational
costs
are higher than they would be because of COVID.
And I know that's not the purpose of this grant or at least that sounds what it's not like and you could just increase the bridging culvert spending
for the by the additional
amount, you know $90,000
there.
Or
maybe we take some middle road, I don't know.
>> I think if we're gonna take the risk, we just plug the number in here and let the numbers fall where they are and we'll figure it out next year.
>> I mean, that's where I'm starting to go with it. That's why I asked the technical question of if we just throw it into the revenue
and then we get the guidance and we get the grants written and whatever
when it comes time to spend it.
Do if we need to take any further action as a board. Let's assume the budget passes we get through that.
And then we get clarity on where we can spend this money.
Do we need to come back and say, okay, we're now gonna formally allocate that stuff
to this, that, the other thing.
>> But remember, if you're wrong,
there's $160,000
Shortfall. You know, shortfall in an already
really
tight budget.
Yep.
That's gonna hurt. We
>> can always find
other ways to spend it,
to take it out of where we put it
and reallocate
it. That
>> happens all the time. We can probably find an acceptable use but Eric's point still stands if we take it out of another line item we still got to make up that amount. Well,
>> my
thought processes that we need to find out what it is that we need to spend this money on or can spend this money on. So I'm willing to do some research and call around and
talk to
people who are in authority, just like we have on the school side,
people are program managers of certain grants.
They know and they can tell us.
And then I could have something emailed to me
with a variety of ways to spend it rather than just
sitting here guessing
what would be good and what not to be good. I think that would be a worthwhile
>> conversation to have. I think it would be most useful if the people you talk to are in similarly situated towns, rural towns that don't have city sewer and whatnot
that are similarly situated that have the same sorts of that at least when you look at this thing on its face
are looking at the same hurdles.
>> Sure.
But I agree that's a worthwhile exercise but I want to point out from a practical standpoint, we have a week, we have to have a budget tonight unless we're all I understand that.
>> I'm just saying,
I'm just saying if we want to just go and put this
where we want it,
and then reallocate or adjust it later,
there's time
to do that.
>> Do we have anything
further on the audit? Has there been any
finalization
there?
We're closer,
there's no change. Pretty close,
but
I haven't heard anything.
>> But the number we have to work with isn't changing. It's not getting better. Let's put it that way.
>> No, it's not what it was really getting at. I was
thinking about it from the standpoint of,
this drags out or it's a disaster scenario where we're wrong or something
that we still have some fund balance that I love to use
except
in case of disaster.
But I was just trying to think of where we're at. We're using a little fund balance this year, kind of the last time around to plug holes in our capital budget.
And that's gonna leave us with
what 11%
right
after we do this
in terms of our
savings.
Yeah, not a lot. If we're still above
the 10% target, we may have some play is kind of what I'm saying.
If in the any absolute worst case scenario,
which again, I of
have to think that ultimately
Sherry and Valor, right, we're gonna figure this out.
I just, I'm struggling with it too from the standpoint of budgeting when you have this
question mark.
>> Well, one thing we could do is take a middle row, we don't need to allocate, we don't need to assume that we're going to be able to
apply all $159,000
against
the projects we're planning, know, maybe we could also just say maybe it's 50,000,
you know, maybe it's 25 maybe it's 100.
So there might be a middle road and then if it turns out we have an opportunity we get the 159 ks we figured out that there's more ways to spend it we come up with some creative stuff. You know we, we, we put in a,
you know, lavish water fountain at the
Veterans Memorial Park or something you know that you know that that's all
that
that's all positive right that's all in that.
>> Okay talking about showing
this grant as a revenue item.
Okay just losing any expenses.
>> Just so you have it.
Is what came
from office of fiscal analysis at the state
and this the,
you know, kind of use of funds.
Workers who perform essential work or provide grants to employers with employees that provide
essential work.
You know,
government services
to the extent of lost revenue
from the public health emergency, which is not applicable to this down because we haven't really lost any revenue per se.
You know, and investments in water sewer and broadband infrastructure.
Yeah. I mean, that's a pretty freaking vague,
you know,
and I'm sure there will be
a lot more detail but we just don't have it yet.
>> Also point out the language in the next section that says following
restrictions.
So it's clearly states not just reduce tracks is directly but also indirectly.
>> Right,
that's what I'm saying. Mean, I think to think that you can just apply this to the budget
legitimately
is
to me does not seem correct.
And I'm not sure there's not some kind of budgetary gimmick we can do to make that happen. There may very well be but
you know I'll make sure you sign that one not me.
No problem.
I mean the word indirectly
>> is problematic.
Yeah, I mean, character
of it.
Makes me less comfortable than I was before.
Yeah,
that's not great.
>> Between March 3
till the last day of the fiscal year in which the funds have been received, spent or returned. So June thirtieth next year.
>> Just move the next budget year.
Between now and the next budget year.
Yeah.
>> I mean, it's a little frustrating. And this is where you get into semantics. It's like our taxes are going up
regardless.
But, yeah, it's an offset. I know the indirect
that's that's concerning to me. And I almost wonder what
town attorney would make of that or.
>> I mean the town attorney would say wait for guidance. Yeah, I know. Too big.
>> I know, I know. I work with attorneys. I'm very familiar.
>> Right.
I mean, you may very well be right and there may be, we may be able to just plug this directly in. We very well may be able to. It's just a question of what,
you know.
>> I guess the other option which I don't love either.
I'm just sort of brainstorming here
in order to deal with that language
is if we were to cut the capital budget by a certain amount
and then say whatever we get
from this grant will try to throw it capital to make that up later.
I don't know. Don't like it either. Concern
>> with
initial feedback we've got on the budget is there was a lot of talk about the capital and kicking the can and the roads and, you know, the trees, And
I don't know if we cut capital that people are gonna vote this to go to referendum.
Yeah, I know.
>> I was
surprised by that those comments in the last meeting.
>> Mean,
get that. I mean, it's reality. We have done that.
So we have capital
needs. Eric talks about all the time. We have this backlog.
>> The community center.
Well, that's for community center.
That's for the benefit of the community,
making I it
>> would hope that all that we're doing is for the benefit of the community, but I I know. But I mean, in particular What
>> are we loading into that capital fund this year? We're adding $50,000
>> but we're already spending 50,000 this year, you know, in this budget cycle.
We're just looking at status quo.
Going forward and we're probably not gonna be breaking ground on that next year by the way things move, but
there will probably be things with the community center that we can use these grant funds for like the relocation of the septic, if it's broad enough. Solar,
we're gonna put, I don't know if solar would even
kind of qualify in that infrastructure.
>> It's odd to me that they didn't include power infrastructure.
Right. Because that's clearly- I have to.
Mean. Yeah the water thing just seems so
antiquated oddly narrow.
>> Is oddly narrow. Water and sewer yeah. You know and that's been a huge topic of discussion among the town administrators
Cause they put in one word, water infrastructure.
Can we spend that on culverts?
Is that only
water
supply?
Can we pay for that to drill wells?
You know,
probably
maybe all of the above
you know what
I don't know
maybe we could give it to Alcoa I don't know yeah you know I don't it
is frustrating to be at the point this far along in the budget process
know you're getting money and not know what you can use it for.
>> Wouldn't be talking about this if they didn't cut our educational cost sharing.
>> Well, Right. Maybe we should have been anyway. That cut anyway but.
Yeah.
That's, yeah.
We
>> know we've gotten the town aid roads,
can we use that to offset something instead of this ambiguous
grant?
Mean We're spending out on the roads right?
>> Spend 100% of town aid road money on roads. I
know I'm just trying.
Yeah, yeah.
I guess
>> I'll say that given the language that I just read I'm uncomfortable
personally
budgeting,
adding this as a revenue line item to the budget.
This late in the game without the ability to further explore and I think there's a probably a very good opportunity for us here to do something
that we wouldn't have done otherwise, but I'm not sure
given the language that
I'd be comfortable
adding that line item, which is obviously different than I thought a few minutes ago.
>> Mark, I agree with you on that.
I'm thinking more that it's going to cause more confusion because it's going to be a lot of questions.
Maybe if the hearing is, know, what can we use it for and all that.
And
quite frankly, as far as
submitting this to the town, the budget the way it is right now,
we've kind of gone
around and around quite a bit, and we've kind of gone bare bones.
My thoughts are to present it the way it is without
that extra money in there
and see what the town says.
If we
can reduce,
hopefully we'll get some feedback from them
and us,
because we're them,
to
determine
where that reduction
will come from.
>> That's my thought on that. Yeah, I tend to agree with you, Luis.
>> I do think we can mention when we present it to the town that look,
is not in the budget, somebody may ask, look, this you may have heard we are gonna get some grant money from the feds. It's not in the budget and here's why. And right now we just don't feel comfortable bringing you
a budget that includes this because of the ambiguity and then move on
without trying Yeah to
>> and say later that if we get it it's a plus.
>> Right yes and anything we can do to
defray, I'll try not to say offset,
you know to benefit our town you know. Defray, offset yeah.
It's frustrating because I just
think of like money is fungible it's so dumb. I know right.
>> Well but because I mean honestly
every town would do the same thing you guys were just contemplating just plug it into the budget and reduce taxes
which is exactly the opposite of what this is designed.
>> It's designed to be a stimulus package Yeah. Just to reduce taxes. And again, and that's fair if you were talking about towns doing that to literally reduce taxes.
We are trying to defray a tax increase. We've already got coming.
You know it's a little of a lot to me that's. Sure you're not a lawyer there, Robin.
I worked with them for twenty years they rub off on me what can I tell you? I think the language is all right. Know your honor I see a distinction here okay
this is distinguishable
but no I kind of agree I mean on the other hand I flip flop a little bit on this you know it's our job as a board to try and
do what we can and bring them a budget that is workable.
Not bringing the budget from the CCS curveball.
>> It's really late in the game. Think we had something I think we were more or less comfortable to go to the town with and now we're looking at this $62,000
>> problem. I have a question. What does it cost us to do a referendum
to do a vote? Because I'm
fully expecting
it to fail the first time.
>> Well I think probably if I were to guess Diane what's going to happen is it will fail
at the budget meeting
and it won't even go to referendum
and it will come back to you
in a couple of weeks
to try again.
But I mean, could be wrong, you know, I,
>> you know, my It's funny because I feel like we had this conversation before the meeting started that people seem agitated, the whole COVID thing, everybody's on edge and people are picking on things and
there's just a lot of, I hear a lot of disgruntled people out there.
>> To try to answer the original question. I thought didn't the referendum cost us about $2,000?
>> Yeah
I think 2 to 3,000 is probably a realistic number
because remember we still have to send out an official notice so we got a mailing cost
and then we got a cost for all the poll workers
you know and we got to get our memory cards updated and there's a bunch of
there's a fair number of expenses you wouldn't think
as part I of
>> remember it costing and my number is probably out of date it's
probably like you say it's probably higher now. I remember it being about 2 ks but that was years ago.
So I wouldn't be surprised if it was 2 and a half 3,000 to run a referendum.
So it's not nothing but it's also not eye popping.
We obviously want to try to avoid taking something to a referendum that we think is gonna fail.
But I think it's a good point to point out that a lot of the times if it's really a tough budget, comfort controversial budget, it doesn't make it out of the meeting. Right, and then we'll know, right? I mean, we'll have some guidance that
>> obviously that can change one meeting to the next but then that does give us some guidance about where the real, you know, feeling is, I mean, I think we, we know where some of the
some of the angst is in this budget, clearly,
on
what the appetite of the
other residences for this,
you know, it's.
Yep,
>> it's a hard call. Yeah. Linda, do you have any thoughts,
Dave, about
the idea of passing it on as is?
>> I don't think it'll pass, but
I don't know what to do at this late date. So I think it's as is.
We
could reduce our expenditures.
>> Mean, have a problem. I'm
uncomfortable
cutting more,
well really anywhere but cutting more from the AAS budget where he took a whack at it and we don't really know
specifically what it would do.
Think we cut like 40 some odd so that now if you threw it all on AAS now you're up to 100.
If we go to cut it out of town budget I'm not sure where we find it.
To take it from capital budget
>> which we, which we've been we shorted the capital budget last year, and we've heard this, I think it was Diane pointing out surprising how much or maybe it was Lee's how much people felt commented on that unless there but public hearing other meetings.
Sorry, Dave, did you want to
>> add my yeah my comments.
Same as Louise just kind of I think go as is,
and
town shoots it down.
Then I have no problem looking at some line items.
Yeah. The cut
kind of off topic. Just wanted to make a comment on that
money due to the COVID
relief.
Not really similar, but in my business, we had a chunk of PPP money and in the beginning we didn't really know what to do with it so I just kind of let it sit there in a fund.
So we've, you know, got some guidance from SBA it was ridiculous trying to get rules and regular. So,
as a town, we should probably same thing with that money.
>> Don't spend it before you know you got it basically right.
>> Yeah, just let it sit there until we get some
clear
clarification
of rules.
>> Alright, so it sounds like there's some appetite to.
Take the budget as is with the changes that reflect the reality of the likely educational cost sharing reduction plus the.
More clear number on the
combined position
savings.
And maybe just roll that into the recommended budget.
Any further discussion on that?
>> I just want to piggyback on that and just say that you know you use the word well likely reduction of ECS you know given that that's not final we're budgeting intelligently I think you do
budget for that bad scenario
but it's not a guarantee either.
Do we have any sense
for the legislative time frame on this Eric
from the state
on when they may actually enact that?
Mean they guide this way out.
You know I'm not
now. Yeah,
the only thing
>> you have going for you is you have a
democratic governor and a democratic
legislature.
I mean, of the question is, you know, the governor wasn't really too excited that the legislature
added a ton of money to
the ECS.
So that you know the total appropriation
for educational costs savings
went up $180,000,000
So they added a lot of money to it but then they changed the formula enough
that it negatively affected us so they're actually putting a lot more money into it we're just not
>> getting to take advantage. Yeah they're refocusing where it's going
but or at least that's the proposal.
The sausage gets made in the when it comes down to assemble
the votes to pass it.
And I know in the past and this is a bit of a third rail and
there was a year where this dragged out so long. We had finalized our budget and months later the legislature finally got around to doing what they were gonna do and we actually got lucky that year.
I
don't think we can count on any such thing but just sort of in the back of our heads remember that's not a done deal.
>> Right
so and just so that we're all clear
you know we're talking about basically
a 1.36
increase
if we go
as is right now with the spending we've outlined. Am I correct Mark?
>> Let me get to the right page.
What did you say Eric? 1.36?
Yeah 1.36
mil.
Went from 35.61
to 36.97.
>> Yeah once I take this grant out of there that I just popped in here.
I have 3.83%
increase to 36.97
mil, right?
>> Correct,
correct. Yep, okay. I just wanted to make sure
're both working off the same
sheet.
And that represents basically
a 0.9%
increase
in the actual budget,
a total of a 0.9%
increase.
>> Which by the way was a question I got hit with today that I didn't have at my fingertips.
Reporter for the river east called me and was trying to get that particular number. She had the raise by taxation number but not that. I said off the top of my head I don't remember. But I knew it was low. I didn't know it was that low. She called me too. I wondered. I was in a meeting. Told her and I told her I was like Mark just got back from Germany.
Could have given it to him. I can look it him. Can get back from you she's like well my story is doing forty three minutes I said well okay
>> I'm at work. Yeah, was the same for me. Okay.
All right. So that's the answer. Yeah, I think we do, we think we do have the,
we're on the same page Eric.
This is, you know, this is what I have
based on that taken out the grant that I popped in there to do a little what if.
But it does provide an estimated mill rate of 36.97,
which is a 3.83%
increase over the current mill rate. So that is where we are by adjusting the educational cost sharing to the likely level,
and then clarifying the
cleaning or more accurately depicting the savings from the combined position.
Yeah. Okay.
>> So that being said,
we can discuss further or somebody can introduce emotion
related to this budget.
>> I move we take this budget as is to tell me. Okay,
>> to, I second that to clarify yours, your, you are motion, the motion on the table is to
recommend the town budget
that was presented at the last meeting with the clip with the addition with the correction of the combined budget plus the
reflection of the 67,000
roughly decrease in the educational cost sharing numbers right consider that a friendly amendment. Yes.
Yeah. Stating that probably. Yeah, I think you're clear which budget we're talking about. Yes, absolutely. The modified budget, those two changes made. Okay, that's exactly how we should say that that's better Thank you. And then Louise you seconded. Yes, I do.
Okay, do we have any further discussion.
Okay, hearing none I'd like to call for a vote all those in the board of finance in favor please say aye. Aye.
Aye. Any opposed.
We have any abstentions.
Okay, motion passes Thank you everybody.
That will be our recommended budget to be presented to the town meeting next Thursday.
Okay,
let's move on to our
next
agenda item, which is item five, which is the town administrator's report. Eric, the floor is yours.
>> So I'm not going to give an
administrator's
report for this one just because I think
it's going to be a long meeting by the time we get through everything we need to get through. So I think we can hold off and I'll give you another one next month unless there's specific questions. Yeah, anybody have any specific questions for Eric?
>> Okay, I guess that's,
that's good then. Thank you, Eric.
Okay, that takes us to item six on the agenda, which is finance department report.
Number one is the town budget summary
six a.
>> Okay,
so before we start,
does anybody have any questions on the budget summary for either myself
or Sherry Holmes or Sherry?
Are you gonna share Eric or?
>> I was well, what I was gonna share,
if people didn't have specific questions
is
just,
I went through
the
town budget
and I identified
all those areas,
you know, based on what we've expended
so far
where I think we're going to be over in those areas that I think we're going to be under.
So
going down the overages,
there's some fairly
significant ones we can talk all of them
about them in general
but the bottom line is if you add up everything that's an overage
you know you come to a total of somewhere around $150,000
and if you add up all the things in our budget and that $150,000
includes
the Board of Selectmen's desire to transfer money
to
spend on the Veterans Monument from the COVID relief funds
in an amount of $20,000
And it also includes
what they had and you and we had talked about,
which is a transfer of money from this year's budget into the tree work permanent fund
to offset because we decided not to put that money, the increase back in
next year's budget. So with those two items in
that comes
our total number of things we're over on is about $149,000
And on the other hand if you look at the areas where we're under spending the bunnies sorry that should be underages not overages.
>> I was gonna say.
You Brad I was confused. Yeah.
I just had a heart attack.
You.
>> So
the total amount of money that we're talking about where we've under spent
is
as close as I can tell somewhere around 180
or $182,000
Now there's going to be other small things this is going to go up and down a little bit but you know but this is the broad categories of the big things you know we haven't
spent on.
So the good news is and this does include contingency
so if you look at the difference between the overages and the underages
at this point that means we're spending roughly 10,000
of
the contingency money
just to even up the budgets if we take those two, if we do do those two things we're talking about the you know spend the money on Veterans Monument Park
and the transfer to the tree fund.
>> Wait so hey our king hi hang on a second so the net between these two
it is roughly $32,000
and then you're saying
that but that $32,000
includes pulling 10 from contingency?
>> Well actually it includes 18,000
from contingency if you think about it because I'm putting all of contingency
in in here in the under expended because we haven't spent anything from contingency.
So we're basically at this point looks like we're going to be spending around 18,000
out of contingency
If we do those two things that both you and the board of selectmen have asked to do,
know that means we're our margin of error is down to about 32,000
>> something in that range. Okay but that's helpful and we you know give or take that amount if nothing else changes terribly much that's sort of what we're looking at for kind of our end of year
result.
>> Yeah, somewhere in there. I mean, that could change. That's
me spending
five or six hours going over the budget. So
I'd certainly welcome
Sherry checking my math on that.
>> Marina and I had talked about this today
and
we're going to sit down next week and go through
the rest of the expenditures including the Board of Ed
expenditures,
making sure everything is recorded on both sides
and reconciled.
And then
we'll be able to give you a truer
number
at the next meeting in May. We had talked about having a firm number as far as where we feel that we're going to land.
>> Yeah, that's the one thing that could screw my calculations
is if there's something big that hasn't been actually inputted into.
But I think,
>> yeah, I think you've pretty much put everything into it. I think so, but there's a couple things we had talked about today that I want to make sure get
in there and accounted for.
>> So consider this very preliminary,
but you know why I'm trying to zero in on this is that if we actually end up having $30,000
lying around in contingency,
I can't remember last year if we had much left in contingency and what we did with it but
that's also potentially found money.
>> So last
year at
the end of the year we transferred
the majority of our remaining money
into the permanent funds. So we could essentially roll it over and not have it hit unexpended fund balance.
But
>> I think we probably could safely
do the transfer
to tree work
and I know
you've talked about that and the Board of Selectmen has talked about that
so whether you do it now or you choose to wait a month or two,
the advantage of doing it now is
we do a little better with the tree service because right now
most towns in the state are waiting on the next fiscal year. Most people have blown through their tree budget so right now they have time and availability.
So there's some advantage to having the money now
but it's not a
you know,
it carries some risk.
>> I mean, personally, given
the amount of play we have there, I'm comfortable with it.
I
don't think we're gonna suddenly find that there's $30,000 in expenditure we didn't see coming.
>> Well,
we just broke a public works truck that was,
you know,
50 something thousand dollars.
Oh, thanks Eric. There's
>> an awful lot of things that could break,
that could come up with a big bill.
Yeah, okay. Just don't break anything else.
That's my intention.
>> I'm glad to hear that.
So
it sounds like Erica what you're proposing is that we would need to make that motion to.
To transfer
some funds to the tree work.
Fund.
>> So you at
the meeting about the last regularly scheduled meeting about a month ago
wanted a
we're considering a motion to do that. Yeah.
And
honestly, I didn't have my act together to give you exact line items,
you know, where it's coming from and where it's going to.
So you have that information now if you choose to do it, you can make that motion now or you can wait.
>> That's kind of your fault you were proposing moving it from the computer services fund
01/9735
to the tree work fund correct
correct
I thought we were taking it from COVID funds.
>> Not that.
Not that, okay. No, because we've pretty much accounted for all the COVID funds dealing with
the Veterans Monument.
So we're taking it from the software implementation?
Correct. Okay.
Correct.
So,
well,
>> So in essence, we have less money. Yeah. What about the fact that we talked about
>> that the school paid for the software
we
were going to
reimburse for
50%.
We're still not doing that?
I'm just wondering.
Because
we
Oh, we've been liquidated.
>> 34,000
is what they pay.
And
they were expecting
to get back half of that.
>> That hasn't really actually been part of the conversation. That might have been the original plan. I haven't heard that. It was just kind of they wanted us to recognize that the school had borne the burden of the entire software
cost.
>> See I wasn't here or part of the conversation so I'm just,
you know, researching
and talking to people and, you know, I don't know. I'm just trying to get a handle on what
it should be or shouldn't be. That's all.
>> Think with that educational cost sharing stuff coming in higher and sticking it in the budget, we have to leave it the way it is.
Don't have any extra money.
>> It's a different budget year but what are you are you suggesting that we don't touch the contingency fund Diane? Because that's really kind of what we're talking about in a way. I mean, I'm saying I don't think we have money to reimburse the school 50%
>> for the software.
They were, I thought they took that money out of excess money from
COVID savings.
I can't remember, correct me if I'm wrong on that. Thought that was coming out of
last budget year we were talking about spending money ahead of time.
And that was one of the items.
>> We we can keep that out right now.
Sherry's
right that that was the conversation. But Diane, yeah,
you're you're you're you're okay with that. I don't want to interrupt you guys, but go ahead with the conversation and
>> Well, I was gonna ask you kind of what your take was on it anyway.
>> Right. No. She was right to ask because she's right. In our notes, it said that we were waiting for that as well as $4,000
reimbursement for computers and stuff
>> for the cost of the merger. She's absolutely right. That was in the notes. So the reason why it didn't get done was because there was no account number in the budget.
And so
we made sure that we set up an account number now for that $30,000
and made sure it was identified
because that was the missing
link.
Sorry, that's my dog. You had made the
decision and the motion and everything to
transfer that money, 30,000,
into the budget and to be earmarked for the software
system or whatever you want to call it.
But it didn't get done by
the previous employee because there was no account number
that she could identify
to bring it into the budget that way.
So now we have set up an account number and brought it in to where it should be
in the budget.
>> Sherry Now the town still owes you the $4,000
that we've agreed to.
Yeah. Maureen had told me the other day she never sent it,
>> I but was assuming that the town had paid that I doubt. A while ago. So so so let's put that let's put that part on hold
because,
you know, Eric, give me and I'll be in Friday. Give me and Sherry a chance to look through
because if we can do without it and and just gift that 34 to the town,
we will. So Sherry's right. That's what it says in there that that money's supposed to come to us. But we haven't quite gotten to where you are, Eric, with this list yet. Sherry and I are still working on overages and underages.
Underages,
if that's even a word, underages. But
if we don't need that,
give us a week so that we don't do it. But but if we don't need that to survive between now and the end,
then
we will gift that to the town as part of something already paid and not ask for that back.
So give us a chance to look at that. But Sherry is absolutely right that Laura had left that written in there that that's what we were waiting for. And
>> the other thing at some point we're gonna have to come to terms with is that the town has budgeted for the whole cost
of paying the auditor.
And
you know for whatever reason two years in a row
the school has reimbursed us half the cost of the audit
but
I don't have any documentation as to why you've done that. Mean you have done that.
>> It was the budget to be nice.
But but I don't think we planned to do that, Eric. But I do know that we planned
to also pay all of Sherry's salary in our budget even though that was supposed to be split for next year. So, you know, we haven't asked for that yet either.
I I have that in our budget as well. So her whole salary. So, you know, between
Sherry's half of the salary, the 30,000
for or half of the 30,000 for the software and the 4,000 for setting up the two offices,
we have covered that. And I will sit with Sherry and really try to make sure that we don't have to ask for that back.
Is that fair?
So as long as Sherry can sit there with the books and make it happen for us,
and we're not in the negative, then then we won't ask for that back.
>> So so to summarize,
I think that the
the
potential proposal in front of us is to
move the 30,000 from the software fund to the tree work fund, which is something we contemplated in a previous meeting, agreed that it probably was a good thing. But it this has
a couple of risks associated with it. One is that we basically are tapping the contingency fund, leaving only about 32,000
in there
remaining.
And the other thing is that if the school district was to come upon some kind of shortage they might need some help covering that shortage.
If I mischaracterized
any of that.
Nope.
Okay.
So then, in order to take any action we would need to have a a motion to make that transfer of the money from the
computer fund to the tree work fund.
Anybody in the board have any more comments or would anybody like to make a motion to that effect?
I'll tell you what, I'm just normally sent the
chairs
chairs, activity
to make the motion. I'm going go ahead and do it. So I think it's,
it's probably appropriate. And I think it's relatively safe to slate in the game, but I'm going to motion that we transfer $25,000
or we have $30,000
Your motion Elliot took $25,000
in there, but we'll say $30,000
from account 135,
which is computer services to the Treework Fund,
which is 1 hundred-zero-three
thousand 749
for this year's fiscal budget.
And I'll second that motion. Okay, Rob seconds. Any further discussion on that?
Okay, I'll call for a vote for the board of finance members. All in favor say aye.
Aye.
Aye. Any opposed?
Any abstentions?
Okay, motion passes. Thank you, board.
Okay, we will continue
our
agenda items there.
Eric, do you have more?
No, not until
we get down to
>> Let's see. I mean, we're basically a town budget summary. We took some action on the town budget now.
I don't know that we want to We need to review the revenue or tire spending over expenditure report. Any
over expenditures we need to discuss?
>> No, I mean, I gave you a list of all the things that we're gonna be over expended.
You know, there's quite a few. No specific authorization that you're saying.
Right, but
honestly, I don't have my act together to
say exactly where I want to take each one of these from.
And we're in the last quarter so when we do it we'll just make all the transfers
basically in one big final motion.
Okay. That's how I would assume we'll deal with it.
Right.
Any other questions? I
can send you this if you would like it.
>> That spreadsheet you mean? Yeah. Yeah, I'll
leave that to the other board members I'm okay without it. Sherry, go ahead. You have the floor. I just want to point out on the revenue summary
>> is where my focus is going to be right now to make sure that all the revenue
has been properly recorded.
So that report is going to look a lot better.
With that Better how? Being said, well, when I reconcile
the bank statements,
The bank statements only reconciled through December.
And I talked to Laura today, so we've got to reconcile January,
February, March.
And reconciling those, you do discover what
is recorded and what isn't
recorded
in revenue. I believe there are some things that haven't been recorded yet properly.
>> So the numbers actually may change. Yes,
yes.
Not just the other good already. And
>> actually what the auditor is requesting me to take a look at and to do update
the revenues.
So we'll
have that
all
sewed up
hopefully by the next time you see this report. Okay,
>> good. Thank you. I just want to point out too just for people who
don't necessarily have it in front of them that all of the budget detail,
the revenue summary we're talking about, etc. It's all in the Board of Finance packet is on the town's website. You know, we're referring to it as we go through here.
Okay.
Any other questions for Eric and Sherry?
Okay, we don't have any
agenda item seven would be budget transfers,
supplemental appropriations,
over expenditure reports, we have none.
>> None that I'm prepared to give you.
In truth, I should have them for you but I do not and I will readily admit that.
>> Okay let's hope you're over over and under analysis was fairly accurate there then.
Me too.
>> Okay any further questions for Eric and Sherry on the on the budget
budget transfers.
Okay hearing none let's move on to item eight which is old business
eight days of software transition,
what do we have to report there.
>> We were on a call
the other day with
the program manager from Edmonds
gov tech,
And he wanted to get a feel for
our chart of accounts,
our reports that we would be required
to
produce from the software.
We sent them reports for both sides, town and Board of Ed.
And he has emailed me
as of today with a list of other items he would like
us to send them.
So I'll be working on that list as well.
I think overall this transition will go smoothly once we get started.
The actual software is on our server.
There's a little bit of tweaking that they need to do so that we can
have it
go live as far as the training base is concerned,
so that we can start the training on both sides.
We're pretty anxious to get going on that. They will do the conversion
of our data
on both sides, town and board.
And they also are requiring a list from us as far as the account numbers.
So what account numbers we don't want to transfer over,
which I have a report that I will be sharing with them,
all the account numbers that won't go over because they have zero balances and we haven't used them and I don't know
The other
piece on the town side will be a reclassification
of certain account numbers,
getting rid of the very detailed account numbers like brooms or stuff like that.
And this is to
go along with the uniform chart of accounts
on the municipal side
and create accounts that they recognize and everyone else recognizes
to be supplies
like, you know, six, ten and those kind of things. Okay?
So we're going to do some reclassifying
that and changing that.
I will also build a crosswalk
when I'm finished doing that with them
so that it's an easy transition
going from point A to point B.
And the reporting should be actually
a lot easier to follow,
in my opinion. It's just it'll be so much better.
And so that's what we're trying to work with the
programmer with.
I have to have a conversation
about the database,
you know, and how that's all going to work
with them
and just verify what their
direction is going to be in that respect
so that we get
exactly what we should be getting from them.
So
if there's any questions,
I'd be willing to answer them. But I think
that's it for now. We will be on many calls
over this next several months
until we get to the point of the training and then go live
on July 1
is our goal.
That's my goal.
And we're certainly going to work towards that. Good.
>> Sounds like some good progress. I know having been through this a couple of different times in different points in my career, I know it's a big, big job.
>> And Eric was on the call and Valerie was on the call. We were all there
having the conversation with
Eric Leonard, his name is, and he's going to be the program
director of this. Right.
>> And
one of the things I think we still need to work out is
at least the first selectman and the board of selectman was very adamant that we end up with a single database
that encompassed both.
And
the problem we're running into is the town and the school both have different tax ID numbers.
they're not really
set up to handle a single database
with multiple tax ID numbers.
And so that's going to have to, we're going to have to figure out a solution. Either we're going to have to compromise,
and go with multiple databases or they're going to have to figure out how
to make it work. I don't know what the Board of Finance's feelings are
>> on that. What's the practical result when you
say multiple databases Does that mean you just cannot combine the numbers and for reporting purposes?
>> Right. Basically two separate accounts and the Right. The IRS recognizes the town with one
ID number and the school with another ID number. That's how we do the reporting for the w twos. Yeah, and for 1099.
>> Yeah, for the practical purposes though for what the selectmen are looking for you really just can't have combined report now, you're going to have to produce separate reports and consolidate them in Excel or something like that. Well, what has been customary in my
>> experience
is that you have two databases, one for the town and one for the school.
Neither one of you can look at
each other's data.
But what you've done is different
this time around, is that you've hired a finance director
who has access and is linked to both.
So
my point is, if you want to
bring transparency,
what it's going to have to be is that if
you request a report of the Board of Education,
it's up to the Board of Education to approve
that report
moving forward.
I can
work with both town and board
to make that happen.
So it's a smoother
transition
and it's a smoother
working relationship
between the two.
So that's my hope. I will have the conversation with
the selectmen
and
I will explain the situation and how
the software company is
proposing, like any other software company that you would go with, would propose exactly the same thing.
And when I first came here and I heard one database,
I knew that wasn't going to be possible.
Just by virtue of the fact that
you have two different ID numbers, tax ID numbers,
okay? And I realized that was, I think that was the conversation early on and I was not privy to that, but
it's
just something that we have to deal with and
come to terms with,
and I need to have that conversation
with them
on this.
Yep.
>> Okay. So that's where I'm at with that.
Okay. I will
get back to you on
where we're at on
that particular subject and databases
when I finish
having that conversation.
>> All
right, very good. Thank you.
You're welcome. Any more questions for Sherry on the software transition?
Okay, let's move on to the audit status. I think Rob already asked this question in our budget discussion.
Anything to add or?
>> We were supposed to have an audit April 30, because that was the extension
was to April 30. He was going to take this last extension
and then have something to us
by then.
>> Have not received Is there a fight coming after that?
>> No, I haven't received anything either
way.
It's got to be anticipate
that he will be sending us draft soon. Would hope
I certainly can touch base with him tomorrow and send him an email.
Ask him. Where is he at? How's he doing? Does he need anything from us? Because he hasn't reached out and
said that he did.
And then find out from there where we stand.
>> Okay.
Any questions
for
Sherry or Eric on the audit?
Okay, let's the item eight. It see is the motion to transfer the funds from the treasurer's office software to tree work fund. I kind of preempted that with
the motion earlier.
So I think we move on to a d
community senior centers community slash senior center building committee.
We have an update there.
>> Not for me. Diane, you look like you're updates the way we kind of left it. We approve the funds to go out to for the site survey conceptual drawings.
It's kind of in Eric's court to get the bids and do that. I know we're all wrapped up with budget and getting all that stuff done.
So I don't think we're going to see anything until this budget is put to bed and voted on it fast.
>> You
might
there I might get the I'd like to get the RFP
out for the survey portion,
you
know,
sooner rather than later because I don't want to hold that up and that's not very expensive
but
you know
I do have a few other things on my plate.
>> Okay.
All right. Thanks, Diane. Thanks, Eric.
Nothing more on that.
8E is the Veterans Monument Park updates.
Any update on that?
>> So we were able to
bring
in a
well driller,
take the existing
well,
the upper well at the monument,
change out the pump in it to a higher capacity pump
and eventually pump through the major sediment issue that that well had.
It just basically required
pumping the heck out of it for a long time.
So
we're out a total of about $2,900
to rehabilitate that well,
but it's a lot cheaper than drilling a new well. And there's already an existing vault.
So now that we know that what we the next thing we need to do is we need to figure out
you know how we trench
down to the field
but
that's progressing and we weren't planning on doing that till August.
So we've got you know or July or August so we're in good shape right now I think in terms of that project.
Jerry
is
raising a lot of money for
through the Buy a BIC program.
So I think there's he's probably raised 16 or $17,000,
you know, at this point, which is great.
And we're,
you know,
we're trucking along.
That's it.
>> Okay
thanks Eric.
Last diamond under old business is 8F the building and land use department online permitting system.
>> So we've discussed this a few times before.
So
what we're doing is we are switching the building department over to an online permitting system
and we're doing it by just straight passing the cost off to the people pulling permits by
adding in a essentially an additional permit fee for each permit
and the software company will bill us monthly
by the number of permits that the system has
has dealt with so it's essentially cost neutral to the town.
Hopefully we've gone back and forth on contract revisions a few times I should have I'm hoping next week I'll have a contract
to sign
and we should be up and running the goal is to be up and running with that about June 1 and transition to online software
for that.
>> Okay, anybody have any questions for Eric on that?
Sounds like good progress.
Okay, let's
move on.
Our next agenda item is new business.
The first item under new business is 9A,
CIP recommendation for the building alarm system.
There's a lot of text here, Eric, you want to, I don't know, are you in a position to kind of give us a summary
>> of this? Yeah, so basically we looked at a total of four vendors of which we got good proposals out of three vendors
and
the board of selectmen
asked send it to CIP and asked CIP
to rank the vendors based on you know their preferences.
CIP reviewed all the proposals and
felt that
FPT or fire protection team you know was the best overall
contractor
for it.
Know
maybe a little bit more expensive upfront
but better long term costs.
The other real advantages to that is that the elementary school already uses FTP for
their inspection services.
So eventually,
whether
we eventually go to a combined bid that includes
the
testing for the school system
because that's the one thing that's not included in any of our quotes is the testing portion.
This will accomplish what the town needs to do,
which is to transition away from TN, the Tollen Dispatch Center,
which will no longer be willing to do monitoring
and change over to cellular monitoring.
You know, the total upfront costs
is going to be somewhere
you know north of $20,000
and it depends on whether we include
the Andover Museum
or not.
There's
pros and cons the CIP was not convinced
that
the service
quote for that building
was reasonable
so they approved it with for everything other than that
and then asked me to go back to the vendor
and if it gets through you guys
and you actually
agree to spend the money it will go to the board of selectmen
and if they approve it then it will get done.
>> So for the museum you're talking about the burglar alarm or fire alarm or both you're talking about? Both,
>> both.
You know right now there's a really half baked
homeowner special system
that has like a single fire detector
and a motion sensor I guess
but it doesn't really
there's never really any call to the authorities
like I've gotten random text messages from the company saying that the burglar alarm has gone off in the building
but
>> you know right so no I understand but you're talking about omitting from their quote
which part of that for the museum. Whole
>> thing, Mark, I think that what it was is it was a combined
bid for that building and Adrian in particular really
thought that was a really incongruous part of their quote, Like that their quote for everything else made a lot of sense and the quote for that building was
did It's like $13 for the museum. He wanted to push back and have Eric go back to them and say, come on,
work with us here and see what I they
>> mean so the big question for the board of finance is
do you want to approve spending because that will you know currently we have somewhere north of $40,000
left
in the building fund
and
this is going to tap
you know
somewhere between 20 and 25,000
of that to accomplish that.
And what I would suggest since nobody's budgeting
for annual testing
or the monitoring
that probably what's going to have to happen is we're going to spend out of the $25,000
the
town will pay for all the upgrades and we'll pay for the monitoring essentially the monitoring for a year for all the buildings
And then next year when we budget, because then we'll have actual numbers for each,
we'll put it back on the library to pay for theirs and
the school to pay for their monitoring. But for now, I'm saying that we just absorb it right out of that fund and be done with it.
Okay.
The monitoring is not really capital but
>> no it's not and you know and you could try to push the monitoring
out on something else.
And you know it's going to work out differently for each
organization.
Like for the town hall, our costs are actually gonna decrease for monitoring
because right now we're paying for two dedicated phone lines.
And by the time we get rid of the $70 a month for two dedicated phone lines and go to one cell receiver,
you know, we're going to be paying less. We're going to be able to realize some savings
but like several, some of our facilities
just use
kind of like a pass through phone line so their alarm shares the same phone line
like for instance as the library so the library is not going to get rid of a phone line so their costs are going to go up.
So it's we really got to parse it out
building by building.
But we're not unfortunately we had to come up with a budget long before we had any kind of reasonable numbers for this to Okay. Assign
>> So you have a suggested motion here, which is to approve signing contracts with the fire protection team for up to $30,000
for the services.
I think I thought I said 25,000.
That's not what your packet says.
Oops.
>> No, I think they got flip flops mark remember earlier,
there was one that was 25 that needed to be 30 and.
Unless
I sent you a wrong.
>> I'm
looking at page 33 of the packet.
The motion to approve as a number of 30,000.
>> Okay,
I sent, I sent to all the board members
a.
>> Oh, yeah, I see you have 25,000
and the more detailed motion and in the email that you had sent. Okay, I see. Yeah.
Yeah.
All right, you got a little discrepancy there. Yeah, the confusion. I just want to say for the record that in this kind of situation where you're running comparative costs, especially with it is different.
Upfront versus you know ongoing running costs, it would have been really nice to have that in a matrix where you have each, each vendor and then what's the upfront costs what's the annual costs, rather than having to tease it out of the text. And I don't know that that's you or the tip but just going forward it's just much easier to, you know, trying to sit here and figure it out on the fly.
Yeah,
Fair point.
Anybody
from the board have questions
on this.
>> Hi, I'm just concerned. So if if the if the old town hall isn't included, are we happy with what's there.
No
>> God no I mean what's there doesn't work. It sounds like what Eric saying is that they're going to go back and rebid
that piece or push push back on that on that part of the quote. Okay, now you're not implying that you're not going to have do something there that's in line with what you're doing for the rest of the town. I mean, I would certainly to me,
>> given what's stored in the Andover Historical Society at the museum,
I would feel more comfortable certainly if it had a working
fire alarm system. But
it doesn't now.
But you know honestly a lot of our buildings don't really have functional systems right now so
you know
>> the insurance guy in me is going la la la la la I can't hear you so
but no the intention yes is to go and try to
juke that bit a bit,
try to get them to come back counter counter offer it a little bit
and then hopefully
we do get that included right. Yep, that's my goal.
Yep.
>> Other questions.
Okay, would anybody care to make a motion on this, we do have a proposed motion language and then email from Eric there is a
not quite
as detailed motion and then in the meeting packet with a $30,000
figure, but
>> Sorry Eric, how much do we need now? Is it 25?
I think we can get away with 25,000.
Okay.
>> I mean we could definitely get away with 30,000
but I think it's doable at 25,000.
>> Including
the museum.
Possibly once you get a revised quote.
>> Yeah.
So
I guess,
so as
written,
I moved, let me just look at this for a second.
Do we want to have anything in this motion that says pending
further discussion with FTP about
the museum?
Or do we leave that out?
>> My thinking is we put some money in the waters I mean the first slackman is going to take a crack at this Eric's gonna you know I think I trust Eric to negotiate a reasonable
contract I think we need to get this done.
Okay.
But that that's my opinion.
>> Yeah, I hear you, and I'm okay with that. So, I'll move to authorize the town administrator
with currents the board select man to expend up to $25,000
from
line item one hundred-three
thousand seven hundred-fifty
two
building maintenance fund to hire fire protection team for fire alarm, cellular monitoring, installation, repair monitoring and annual inspection services at the Andover Town Hall, AES library fire department and public works.
>> And you want to add the old town hall Andover Museum, if
can be handled under that budget number.
>> Oh, okay so that's what I was kind of asking before. I'm sure
if it can be done in that number yes absolutely we should add that correct.
So maybe and or
the
old town hall slash Andover Museum. Correct. Yeah, it sounds.
Anybody want to second that motion.
I'll second
>> Linda seconds. Thank you. Any further discussion.
Okay hearing none let's vote
all those in favor say Aye.
Aye.
Any opposed.
We have any abstentions
Okay, motion passes. Thank you.
Okay, let's move on to our
next agenda item that is item
9B
request for funding for the planning and zoning commission to hire a consultant to develop an affordable housing plan
in accordance with the new state law.
So Eric, you've got a fairly complex,
or maybe not you with Planning
and Zoning Commission, or maybe this, I guess it's out of Andover. So you have a contract for preparation of the affordable housing plan.
>> Right, so let me talk you through this and I'll tell you,
you as a board may or may not be comfortable pushing this forward right now without it going to RFP.
Your guidelines
will say this should go to RFP first. But
the Planning and Zoning Commission is essentially asking
whether you would be willing to sole source it
for kind of two reasons.
One,
the town has a really good history
with Bill Warner.
In fact, Bill Warner and I wrote a grant
that produced most of the data that's going to go into the affordable housing plan
about six years ago
that we funded
and then paid Bill to
do the actual work for.
The reason why I think it's worth
going with Bill on this one is because he wrote our last plan of development,
our last two plans of development
and he did an affordable housing study
on the town.
So he's probably in the best position
to put
together now our state mandated plan.
And so on that basis,
planning and zoning commission asked me whether I would ask you whether you would consider sole sourcing it or whether you want this to go to F, you know,
an RFP.
>> Just the point of terminology sole source basically means you're only to have one vendor do it which is going to be the effective
thing here but you're basically asking us to skip the bid process.
Correct.
Yeah.
So,
looking at the
budget for this, the total budget is $6,900
And
you're saying that in your opinion, and probably in the, I guess, in the opinion of the Planning and Zoning Commission that they're,
They don't expect it going out to bid result in a lower cost for this because the efficiencies that bill Warner would have having been familiar with the
town and the data previously.
>> I mean, I don't think you're gonna get a good plan
cheaper than that. I'm sure we can find somebody that will make us meet the minimum statutory guideline
for having a plan for them not reducing town funding
for less than that. But in terms of doing an actual affordable housing plan that makes sense for the town of Andover,
I think he's gonna, that's gonna be a fairly competitive number.
But without going to RFP,
I can't tell you 100%
sure that that's the case,
just that that's my gut feeling.
>> To be clear our guideline is five ks right?
That we bid out if it's more than 5?
>> No
for services in this category you have no minimum for your guideline
So if
we were paying them a buck, technically we would still be supposed to be sending this out to RFP.
And I think at some point we,
the Board of Finance, once we're through with this year's budget,
really ought to take a look at your policies and start thinking about whether they make sense to you and what changes you would like. Because I think that a lot of those policies were put in,
you know, under a very different regime
that had some serious concerns about you know what a select board
an administration was spending money on.
That's correct.
>> Right and maybe you have more confidence in me or maybe you have less confidence in me but anyway it's
really your
choice whether you want to because
policy it's not a charter
issue and it's not an ordinance so it's your policy and you can decide to override it if you so choose but I don't want to arbitrarily
override it you know that's
that decision is solely yours.
Right. Kind of looking for a waiver here.
>> If
we're going to waive this, shouldn't we have this request in writing from the planning zoning and their logic set out of why they're recommending this to us?
I know Eric gave us a summary, but we still don't have anything
written
or a written request or something.
Not that I don't want to be bureaucratic,
but.
>> I think you make a very good point, Diane. It would be helpful
for the purposes of record as much as anything else is to provide some kind of summary that
says, look, we've looked at it. There's a reason why I mean, I think Eric summarized it well, and I'm not averse to doing this but I do think Diane has a good point about future requests especially to deviate from policy. If we have some type of summary, know,
doesn't have to be as extensive as what we had for the alarm proposals for example which is you know well done and detailed but in some kind of summary about it would help.
>> Yeah and let me tell you that I personally don't have any heartburn with sending it out to RFP.
This was a request made to me and I said I would pass it on and maybe you guys would agree to it maybe you wouldn't you know so I certainly haven't promised them that this is going to fly that's for sure.
>> I don't know if our chart allows us to go and just
decide to go out of RFP.
So we need to be careful here.
>> Yeah, there's some charter language around that right.
Well, was just looking at that. Not long ago. Think yeah, we need some more guidance here.
>> Okay.
I mean, if you want, we'll just send it to RFP.
That's fine too.
>> The
problem is I don't even know if we can do this.
I have to look at the charter first before I make a decision on it.
>> About going to RFP.
Skipping it. Yeah, skipping skipping the RFP.
Yeah, I think, I actually think David might be right here.
Jason we should know that. So that may be more of a charter based question.
So you reviewed that recently I was a little surprised by some of that but. Alright.
Well, I think that, you know, my personal recommendations like until we have that clarification,
you know, we probably would not authorize it I wouldn't be comfortable with that.
Okay, which means Eric can just go to RFP and you can, you know, we can make a decision based on that by the time the next meeting rolls around,
or we can wait for clarification and it looks like it might be possible then we could make that decision but by the time we get to that point and may, it may well be faster to submit an RP wrapped up in a couple of weeks.
Okay, and of course going to RP does not necessarily mean you have to choose the lowest bidder you can choose the better that's in the best interest of the town, which
still allows you if somebody came in a few $100 less but something was compliant but we didn't feel that it was in the town's best interest to have data that might be questionable and analysis that's not as thorough, then we obviously choose the
proposal that's in the best interest of the town.
Not a problem.
>> Any
further discussion on this.
All right, did anybody want to make a motion.
I'll just note that if we want to hold off on this or
let Eric do the normal RFP process, then we would probably not make any emotion We don't want to make a negative motion. We only want to make a positive motion to do something different.
I think we just table it for now.
>> Okay, and Eric, of course, go out therapy and
we can also follow-up on that afterwards.
>> Okay,
I'll touch base with the chairman of the commission.
>> Okay.
All right, I believe that takes us to
roll back up to see it.
New business item nine C motion to appoint Sherry Holmes town treasurer in accordance with the town charter.
>> Eric, do want to comment on this. Yeah, so, so I'm a little screwed up on this, I had it in my notes that
the Board of Finance had to officially appoint
the town treasurer.
It's actually technically the Board of Selectmen has So
what I would say is motion to recommend that the Board of Selectmen
avoid Sherri Holmes as town treasurer to conform with Charter Section 702I.
>> Administrative positions
Yeah, being said, of Selectmen shall appoint the treasurer shall have all the powers and duties
imposed by Connecticut general statutes blah, blah, blah.
Okay, competitive blah, blah, blah.
>> All right. Okay. Well, I'm is they technically haven't so
you can ignore this too and just leave it in there but or you can recommend that they do that.
>> I'll leave that to the board, you know, there's nothing requiring our recommendation
or approval on this in the charter. So we really it's
a moot point,
other than we put our seal of imprimatur
on there approving this.
So it's really, really up to the board. I don't think it's a bad thing to necessarily have done that but
we don't need to. Okay.
Anyone on the board want to make a motion one way or the other.
I usually wouldn't do the other unless you want to not recommend.
>> Sure, I'll move that we recommend that we appoint Sherry
>> treasurer. Okay,
so Rob moves that we recommended the Board of Selectmen
appoint Sherry Treasurer for the requirements of the Charter. Do I have a second?
I'll second it. Okay, Louise seconds. Any further discussion?
Okay, all in favor say aye.
Aye. Opposed?
Any abstentions?
All right. Looks like you're in our good graces so far, Sherry. Thank you. Motion passes.
>> I know. Thank you very much. I appreciate this. I'm counting on you for the grant money, Sherry. That's working
on it right now.
I'm serious I'm working on it right now.
>> Okay.
This takes us item 90 which is a school and state funding project.
This is really relevant to the educational cost sharing we just talked about right Eric.
>> Yeah, I'm actually not
clear what that is.
I don't think I put it in the on the agenda.
I'm not sure what that's relative to, to be perfectly honest with you.
>> Well, it's kind of a summary, I think of the proposed budget from the appropriations committee
and
it talks about the educational cost sharing formula changes.
I think it's just a review of that.
Right, you know it's the stuff that you just you displayed up there is
earlier about the town by town differential from the governor's budget.
And we have pretty much already gone through this. And if anybody's curious about that, I think somebody asked about the things may have been Louise about how it was calculated.
I think there is at least an overview in there about the weighting factors, factors how they changed.
That's in the packet.
Right.
Somebody have any more questions on that I think we talked through it, and certainly the information is in there in the in the packet.
Okay,
hearing
no more questions or
discussion.
That takes us actually to
agenda item number 10, which is the approval of meeting minutes.
We have four different
meeting minutes that are up for approval.
10A is Wednesday, 03/24/2021
regular meeting minutes. Anybody like to motion to approve those?
Anyone? Separate motions?
Yeah,
probably.
We
could probably do them all the other the other three are Wednesday, March 31,
special budget workshop minutes,
the Wednesday, 04/07/2021,
special meeting budget workshop minutes,
and Wednesday, 04/21/2021
town
budget public hearing minutes.
>> I'll make a motion.
To approve all those minutes? To approve all four of them. Okay.
Anybody want to second that?
I'll second it.
>> Okay, Dave seconds. Thank you. Any further discussion?
Okay, hearing none, let's go ahead and vote.
All in favor say aye. Aye.
Any opposed.
Any abstentions.
Okay, hearing none motion passes
somewhere between one and two in the morning and that last budget
hearing so I'm not sure that
fully there I contemplated
abstaining but
I think I'm probably okay.
All right agenda item number 11 is the liaison reports. Do we have any reports from our liaison
members?
>> Well we already kind of talked about what happened in CIP. Yeah, I don't have a lot to add. I mostly just listened to others
give their expertise
and it was really mostly about that
alarm project. Yeah,
I don't really have much to add there. That's good. Okay.
>> Diane, you kind of talked a little bit about the community senior center already. Anything to add there? Are we good?
I'm just saying no. Okay.
All right. I think that
is the summary of our some of our liaison
opportunities there.
Okay, let's move on to agenda item number 12, which is board open discussions.
Do
any of the board members have anything they'd like to bring between the board?
We haven't talked about already.
Okay, hearing nothing, I guess we move on to item 13, which is our public speak opportunity.
Amanda, do want to go ahead and pull the participants
and see who would like to add any comments?
>> Sure. Okay, we have
a couple of people on here.
Joanne Hebert.
>> Okay. September 1. I just have one
Ultimately,
I appreciated all the discussion on that grant and whether or not to add it.
And I believe you made the right decision.
I just wanted to bring forth
an idea that I didn't hear just in case you guys have to,
you know, budget as
>> presented by all of you that could think about that grant. And if,
you know, once once Sherry and Eric do their
>> Oh, we're losing you here. Joanne, we're having a little hard time hearing you. We're we're it's really breaking up.
>> Let me try that. Any better? Much better. Oh yay. I found the connection. I'll be quick really. Again I was just saying I appreciated all the discussion on that.
Let's can try.
We're
losing you again, Joanne. Sorry.
It's not working.
No comment. I'll send it in.
Thank you.
Thanks Joanne.
Good idea. Okay
next up we have Kathy Plassey and Mike Plassey.
>> I
just want to say thank you very very much to the Board of Finance. I think they did a great job.
I know you did the best you could. And I thank you very much for your dedication.
Well,
you, Kathy.
>> Thank you.
Val Bruno.
I am all set. Thank you. All right, thank you. And I believe we're all set.
>> Okay,
great.
All right, next agenda item would be adjournment. Do I have a motion to adjourn?
I'll make a motion.
>> Okay, Diane motions to adjourn the meeting. Do I have a second?
I'll second. Rob seconds. Thank you. Any discussion?
Bueller?
No.
Okay, hearing none, let's go ahead and vote. All those in favor of adjourning,
say aye. Aye.
Any opposed?
Any abstentions?
Sounds like none, motion passes. I want to thank everybody.
Work's not done, but we move the ball forward a little bit more. So thank you everybody stay well and
we'll see you next Thursday.
Reminder
that meeting is in person.
Yes.
Right. So I don't think there's any provision for remote
participation Is that correct, Eric. That is correct.
Wow.
>> Yeah, so 7PM. Are we in the, are we in the gym or we in the town community.
Yeah,
gym.
The gym at the AES.
>> Okay. Yeah. Will people be able to view it
without participating?
Like a follow-up?
Yeah, follow it.
No?
Don't know the answer to that one.
We're not planning on recording it at this point.
Okay.
>> Are you planning Eric on doing it live where you would need the ViewSonic for people to view it live on Zoom?
>> We're not
because there's no practical way for them to vote anyway so it doesn't really matter.
>> I just don't know if we needed to set it up. That's all. Yeah. No.
>> If someone would want to view it later, will there be like there'll be any
>> notes, any minutes? Unless the CVC is there to record it, which I'm not sure about the plan there. Mean, it's really We
>> could record.
We have the
recorders. We could certainly record the thing
and upload it. It's certainly within our power. The question is what purpose are we serving since
>> know. I mean it's really a documenting what happened I guess is that the town clerk's office is doing the minutes.
>> So the minute the minutes will be there that's really the way that traditionally the results of meetings have been recorded and
legally
posted so.
Thank
you. All right. Thank you everybody.